Hello and welcome to our exam review.
So we are going to be studying
together for our Chem 3A
introductory chemistry exam.
We will be focusing on
chapter 8 through 11.
So the way that this exam review will
work for you watching this video, uh, this
will is a recording of my review session
that was held in the fall semester 2024.
Uh, so what I recommend doing if you are
here to watch is the first part of it.
I have, you'll see below is I have the
chapter, uh, chapter labels for all the
different things we will be covering.
Um, if you are here to learn exactly
what's on the test, that'll be the first,
uh, chapter portion of that review video.
Afterwards, as you can see in the bio
description below, I have a link to the
Kahoot that this video is a part of.
I entirely recommend you go along with
the Kahoot and try to play along with
it, um, so that way you can see what
do you know, what do you not know.
If you end up getting a question wrong,
I have all the questions labeled in the,
the chapter, the chapters of the video.
So you can fast forward directly
to the question that you were
interested in hearing about.
If you want to watch the entire
thing, that's fine too, but you
can kind of skip around to which
questions you need help with now.
Um, so I hope that this video helps.
I hope the review helps.
Um, so this is the edited down version and
let me know if you need any help at all.
So reach out to me, um,
whether it's through email,
discord, or the comments below.
And I hope that this helped
and let's learn and try to
study and review together.
All right.
And I will see you all during our review.
Right.
So if you go through modules, it will
lead you to the study module, which,
um, for this particular test, it's
going to be on chapter 10 on chapter
8, um, chapter 9, and then chapter 11.
So there's a, it's a decent chunk of
material on this one compared to probably.
The other ones, but probably the good
thing is that they're all kind of,
they're all related to each other.
Right?
So what I would recommend
doing first, right?
On this test, as always, is
take some time to yourself and
go through the study guide.
I mean, obviously you're here.
We'll go through it a little bit
as well, but really taking that
time for yourself and just kind of
sitting down and absorbing, right?
And not in the middle of
the night to absorb all the
information, but on your own.
Um, you can always go back to
this recording and watch as many
times as you want to help you
kind of remember all the things.
So, uh, the first thing is
the test is going to be very
similar to exam number two.
Being that exam number two went really
well, it looked like for pretty much
every well, better than exam one
did, at least in terms of score.
So it looked like that was good.
So last time, just to kind of
refresh for what happened, was it
was about roughly about the first
half was pure multiple choice.
And then the second half was multiple
choice, but it had a component
that allowed you to show your work.
So that way you can kind of.
I don't know.
It served as two purposes.
One, I graded on partial credit
if you were on that right track.
But two, it sort of like tricked you guys
into being like, hey, show your work.
So that way, hopefully, you actually write
your work, write your units, and you'd get
the correct answer, was kind of the hope.
And I think it kind of worked because
most people did get it correct.
Um, compared to the multiple choice,
actually, I think the percentage of Like
points without me giving partial credit
was higher because people worked and
actually kind of wrote, went through it.
So.
If anything, it just benefits you to get
that, get that, uh, opportunity there.
So these are all the math ones
that will be on the very end of it.
Um, so when you're kind of going through
these multiple choice, those last 15
are going to be the mathy ones, the,
the balancing chemical reaction type
problems, all, all that, all that
kind of, all that stuff like that.
I tried to put the test in order.
chapter, give or take.
So that way it's not, um, it's not like
kind of shuffling and jumping around
too much, at least like the best that,
you know, you can write stoichiometry
as you guys know, that's everything.
So it's a little hard to do it for
that one, but I, I, I attempted, right?
Like, that was kind of the idea, so
that way you're not, your brain isn't,
I would, as much as I would love it
for you guys to be able to think like
me, it's, my brain is connecting to 4,
000 different things at a given moment,
so it's a little hard to do that.
I don't need you guys to have your
brain fried at all times as well.
Um, so it's a little, a little hard to
be able to think in that, in that aspect.
Um, so what are you going to
be able to get on this test?
Uh, you do get an index card like
last time, but if you didn't notice,
then there we got screenshots
from some of you of like, what?
Like one side, you only get
one side of an index card.
So yes, this exam, you only get one side.
Now, why is it that
I'm taking away a side?
There's a reason behind this,
and it's not to be mean.
It's because on the final exam, I'm not
allowed to give you an index card at all.
So, because it's a standardized
final across all Chem 3A sections.
So that one, I'm trying to kind of
wean you off of it, is the thought.
So, it's gonna be, really you
gotta kind of put what you
think you really need on it.
And probably, honestly, if most of you
really think back to the last exam,
you probably didn't use it all as
much as you think you'd needed it for.
It's more of like a, it's
more of as a comfort, right?
It's like, yeah, you got your card.
It's really good.
You have it, you have it there
if you need it, but you might've
looked up maybe a couple things,
but you might not have needed it.
There are a couple ways to be able
to fit everything on that card.
Um, you know, I don't say
that you have to handwrite it.
If you want to, you can
type what is on that card.
A lot of you.
Did type it and you could fit a crap
ton of information on a typed card.
I think the secret is about anywhere
from three to four font size is the
smallest you can go, depending on
what you can see with your own eye.
So you can shove a lot of
material on that thing.
So you can, you are allowed to
type it, uh, but you have to be
able to read it with your own eyes.
You can't bring a magnifying
glass or anything silly like that.
Um, you have to be able to read
it and it has to be three by
five inches to specify that too.
Um, then I noticed I didn't
even put my units there.
Oh God, look at me being
terrible with units myself.
So it's inches.
Um, but you do get the yellow sheet on it.
So, and I'll give you like the
whole yellow sheet this time.
Um, I didn't really
bother editing it down.
Uh, the green sheet I'll give
you, but I should edit that.
It's only the solubility side.
It's not the polyatomic part.
So only the solubility part.
I don't know why for polyatomics on there.
So it's the, that one side of it
that has the solubility, the strong
acid, strong bases, And the, um,
uh, the gas evolution reactions.
So you have that side and I put
all that information on there.
Um, when it came to the polyatomics,
they're really, I didn't put it on
there cause there's really no, there's
really no polyatomics on the tests
that are like ones that I hope that you
wouldn't recognize by this point, just
because it's one of the ones that's, I
don't know, based on how people are in
class, like they just kind of know it.
Cause I've seen it 48,
000 times by this point.
You know, like, um, I don't know
what, which ones are on there, but
like, let's say if it's nitrate or
carbonate or like sulfate, or those
more common ones that are like that,
they're just, you see them a lot.
What will I be able to give
you on the standard exam?
Oh, that's the next one.
You're worrying too far in the future.
Really, the only thing I can give you on
that one is the PROC table, and then I
can give you that it comes with it, and
then it's like a reference sheet that
has like, The constants on it, and then
it has like a couple conversions on it.
It's nothing like crazy, but
there's really not a lot of
formulas you need to know on it.
It's kind of all things that I don't know.
If you don't pass the final, if
you want, I mean, I'm kidding.
Uh, usually if you're able to pass the
regular exams, usually you pass the final.
Most people do better on the final
than they do on the regular exams.
Um, At least what I've noticed
the past two semesters people
have been doing better on it.
Most people will tell
me the final is easier.
The hardest part is the time component.
So, but we'll talk about
it when we get to it.
So don't, don't worry about that yet.
There's no point in worrying about it yet.
You can't, we got more to go.
We'll review for that when we get closer.
But no, you will, you'll
still pass the class.
Even if you fail the final.
The only reason you would fail the class
is if you were at like, I don't know.
You were already failing or you
were on like the cusp of failing.
And that was what knocked you over.
Yeah.
One crisis at a time.
Exactly.
We let's focus on exam three,
not worry about the final and the
lab practical and all that stuff.
All that stuff first.
All right.
So you are allowed to get that index card.
Um, uh, bring pencil, your
brain, bring your calculator.
Um, make sure you bring a scantron if
you don't, so you don't forget that.
Um, that way you have all those things.
Now some things that I made for
you guys that you have them, uh,
we have our study guide, right?
So we'll kind of like look over
it real quick so we can have it.
Um, you have a practice exam, which is
one of, um, one of my older, older tests.
Um, it's not really the more current
one, but it's probably one of my first
ones I gave when I started at FCC.
And then.
We have flashcards if you want
to, if you want to review any
terminology, some students and
it will print them out, use them.
Um, but really the thing is practicing
problems is the ultimate way to kind of,
um, be able to go through everything.
Um, So if I were to kind of start
here, let's bring up the study guide.
So you can access the study guide
from two, one of two places.
So you can either access it from
the module or you can get it
directly on here and it will give
you what is going to be on it.
Um, so, okay.
So I got a question.
Do I recommend doing
extra time for DSP and S?
Um, it, if you have it, I would say
it's never a bad thing to use it.
If you're okay with it, just
keep in mind that we have our
Uh, team assessment afterwards.
So you'll just have to schedule
your exam at some time, probably
outside of last time, most likely
to fit it, but you can do it.
You're allowed to take it any time
within a few days of the actual test day.
If that's what you want to do, if
you have that, then yeah, use it.
I won't be mad.
I already submitted it to the S.
P.
and that's for others.
So a few.
Um, so looking at some things.
So first thing.
How would I study for this test if
it was me and I was in your shoes?
Um, there's, there's all kinds of ways
that you can really go through it.
It kind of depends on how far back is
your knowledge, I think, at the moment.
If you have like a mountain of work
to do still, that's when it kind
of gets really tricky and hard.
Um, especially if you have a lot
of videos to catch up on, a lot
of homeworks and all that stuff.
I would recommend getting as much
done prior to probably a couple day
window prior to the test as you can.
So that way you can kind of, you need
to be able to study on some things.
So if you were all caught up, what I would
do is first, I would probably, oh, there's
a couple different things I've done.
Some things I've done in the past
that have been really helpful is
I will actually go back through my
notes and I will actually rewrite
all my notes in another notebook.
So I did that a lot when I was a
sophomore, junior and senior in all of
my upper division science courses, and
it was a lot of work to do that, but
it ended up having forcing me to review
through all the things and clarifying
anything that didn't make sense in
the moment when I was writing it down,
because it's pretty much I would do
it alongside of any PowerPoints I had.
Or maybe I would have like
the book open while doing it.
So that way I can kind
of like read through it.
And then I'd be practicing the examples
like as I come across them in my notes.
This was something that really helped me
a lot when I was going through a class
is this where you're kind of rewriting
them and then doing those examples again,
because you have the answers, right?
And you can see like, kind of how,
um, like how to, how did I think
through them when, when I did,
maybe you might be able to see that.
And if you're stuck on something,
you can, you can message me and ask
if you're like, Oh, I saw this in
my notes, but I don't, I don't see
how, how, how you did this thing, or
it doesn't match what I'm getting.
I like, maybe, maybe I made a mistake,
which is definitely happens, you
know, in the videos or in class.
I do, I do it more than I care
to admit, um, I wish I was
perfect, but I'm not right.
Um, so, you know, you could,
you could do that afterwards.
One thing that you could do is this
really is like, is the key is, is
problem is practicing problems.
Now the thing is, there's a
lot of problems that could
exist across four chapters.
Um, probably the most important
chapters on this test, I would
say they're the heavier topics.
That's kind of hard to say.
I would make sure you're okay
with balancing chemical reactions.
I think is, because I try to pick
things I think are the most important
for what you guys would need for the
next step when I'm making these tests.
Meaning like I keep in mind for all the
people that are nurse that are like the
health science nursing majors, right?
What do you need for physio?
What do you need if you're
taking chem 1a the next semester?
So I try to pick those particular
topics when I'm making these tests.
So like balancing a chemical reaction So
one of the things that you're gonna see
like when you're doing those chemical
reactions is like are you familiar with?
Looking at, let's say, the
different reaction types,
can you follow your recipes?
If you don't know the recipes,
well, there you go, that's something
to write down on your card.
So probably while you're studying,
one thing that I would recommend is
if you want to early on, either if
you do the notebook rewriting trick
thing I talked about, or even if
you're like, I'm not gonna go do that.
That's too much work, which is fair.
I mean, it's not for everybody.
You don't have to do
exactly what I tell you.
It's just whatever works for you, you
know, make a card sooner, you know, and
what you can do is while you're studying,
you can start practicing with it.
And you might kind of realize
that you don't need a lot of
the information that's on it.
And you'll kind of start be like, ah,
cross out and you'll remake the card.
Or if you typed it, then you just
like delete that line because it,
it's just kind of taking up space.
Um, so you can kind of boil it down.
So, you know, balancing and
going through and knowing how
to predict the basic things.
Um, when it being that these are
multiple choice though, so a lot of
the questions, I sort of purposely
tailored them to give you like, maybe
like hints along the way, whether it's
like to hint you to the correct answer,
Or it might give you hints for other
questions just to kind of, so keep in
mind that like sometimes I might have
questions that are referring to topics
on other questions that it might kind of
reveal the, not necessarily reveal the
answer, but it might reveal the direction
that's needed to do another question.
So a lot of times I try to lead you
guys brains in the right directions
while designing these things.
Um, so.
Make sure you're okay with balancing.
That's where the end is.
Now, with that, where does
that kind of lead with what
the next most important thing?
It's probably a toss up between
gas laws and stoichiometry.
I think being that most of you have
been voicing that you actually feel
really good about gas laws, I put a
little bit more gas laws on there.
So chapter eight is probably, it might be,
it might be the one with the most, it's
either chemical reactions or gas laws.
I'm not sure it's probably a close
tie, but, um, that didn't go through
and count them, but based on how
many I kind of picked, Uh, with these
ones, you need to make sure you're
okay with the formulas, so write them
down if you don't know them, right?
You need the ideal gas law,
you need the combined gas law,
and then Dalton's law, right?
Because when it comes to the combined
gas law, you can make that into
every other gas law, whether it's
Boyle's, uh, Avogadro's, Charles
law, uh, Gay Lewis Hacks law.
You can, you can create it, um, and that's
all about, like, things changing, right?
So how can one thing be able to move from.
state one to state two or
initial to final, right?
When you're kind of going through
changing that, but make sure you're
okay with doing those kinds of problems.
And really probably the key is,
is when I say by practicing it is
make sure you're okay with reading
word problems and try to find new
problems that you haven't done yet.
You can practice the ones from class.
That's great.
But if you kind of see the
answer, then you're already going
to kind of know where to go.
So try your best to pick new problems.
So what I did was, is I recommended
some from our online textbook.
You know, if you, for some reason,
don't know, we have an online textbook
just to kind of guide your eyes, right?
It's right up here at the very, very top.
We do have a textbook.
So you can go to those
particular questions.
Every semester, I'll have somebody on
finals week being like, we don't have
a text book, and I'd be like, what?
We have one.
It's just free and you
don't have to pay for it.
That's the only reason
why you might not see it.
So, um, you can do those problems.
They're helpful.
Um, you have that option.
Um, another thing you can do too,
is if you are looking for practice,
I included my old paper homeworks.
That are here as well.
So I have a like the blank homework and
then the key to it as well So if you want
to like actually try like a paper based
one, that isn't my up in math you don't
have to deal with the I don't know anxiety
of red checks or green checks or however
you are sig figs then and You just want to
kind of do old school paper homework like
I the test is The worksheets are there.
They They probably are a little
hard, I think, compared to the videos
and the, probably the difficulty
of the tests, but it's, you know,
it's more practice problems.
It's getting exposed to more things.
Um, that's really the idea.
Uh, you could spend time and
go back through videos and
re watch them if you want.
Um, I think with that, I think it's
more important, though, that you
probably Do problems if you are going
to rewatch videos, probably the ones
to consider watching are more like,
are probably the ones that I, that
are like the practice videos more
than anything, like the longer
ones that kind of take everything
and combine them together.
They're always a little bit harder,
but it's because it's combining seven
concepts together into one video.
Um, and those ones are kind of more to
help you guys, um, the, the idea was to
help link concepts beyond when I kind
of designed them in mind, um, and really
we never get that much time in person to
be able to kind of do that much stuff.
So that's why, you know, there
is that video component that
sort of help everybody see,
see all those little details.
So I would say, make sure you're okay
with your conversions, whether it's.
Doing the formulas, uh, pressure
conversions, uh, how to do Kelvin, right?
Celsius to Kelvin, um, how to go from
atmosphere to tour to millimeters
of mercury, all that kind of stuff,
um, I think are really important.
And maybe the basics of
how gases work, right?
Being that we did talk about
kinetic molecular theory, right?
That's how we describe a gas.
It's like a billiard ball that
doesn't interact with anything.
Make sure you're okay and describing it.
Um, are there any kind of questions about
The guesses or any of that stuff so far
to make coffee before this
the way I stay energetic.
Okay, um, well, in the meantime, uh,
after that, I would say with the aqueous
stuff, there's probably not, there is
some chapter nine problems on there,
but it's like, try to shy away from
making any crazy concentration problems.
You will have to do a molarity problem.
You will have to do a dilution problem.
I don't think there's anything with
molality because I think it's the devil.
Um, I don't think there's anything with
percents on there that I can think of.
I don't think I did.
I'm now I'm gonna now I'm gonna
realize we went on there and it'll
be like, ah, like, hey, dollars.
I won't be on there
Likes malady.
Oh malady is like, I I don't know.
I think it's made up No, it's real.
It's real, you know,
it's just I I don't know.
I don't see the purpose of it anymore.
So molarity is on there.
Um, you will have to make sure
you know when to use the dilution
formula or when to use molarity
as a conversion factor, right?
Molarity is when we use that one
more for Um, solution concentrations,
and then for doing unit
conversions in a chemical equation.
The dilution formula, this is where a lot
of people make a mistake, is only for when
you're making something less concentrated.
Um, so look for the keyword
diluting when you're using that
C1V1 is equal to C2V2 equation.
It's only for diluting.
Stoichiometry uses molarity.
Or molality.
It can use molality too, but
we never did that in class, so.
You guys are okay there.
In terms of properties, um, I
would say make sure you're okay
with understanding the definitions
between, um, aqueous reactions.
That's probably one of the areas I
kind of find to be more important just
because Many of you are studying biology,
the biological body, or the body as
a whole is made of 70 percent water.
So you have to be able to understand the
relationship between water and solute
solvent solute relationships and how
we can describe a solute, a solvent,
a solution, and how that kind of works
within the body and understand the basics
of whether it's colligative properties
or no, how The basics of intermolecular
forces that kind of tie into it as well,
like knowing a water hydrogen bonds,
like how can you see a hydrogen bond
and how that interaction entirely works.
Um, and being that it is such a heavily
used part of physiology, especially
when you start learning about, uh,
cells and the, the blood system and how
red blood cells work or how the cell
membranes work and all these different
things with the fusion and osmosis.
Thanks.
And a lot of you probably, if
you're taking anatomy now, you might
already, especially if you're taking
A and P1, you might have already
been exposed to a lot of these
things because in class, everybody
was, hydrophilic and hydrophobic.
So you already kind of know.
So you need to make sure you're
okay with those, those basics,
um, with, with chapter nine.
Uh, after that, stoichiometry.
Oh, I forgot.
I didn't actually,
maybe that's still okay.
Okay.
Okay, I ignore the part
that says minor part.
I forgot to kind of edit this from the
last time I gave this exam, from summer.
I thought I edited it.
I guess I didn't save it.
The only part of stoichiometry
that I put on there is I put
mass to mass stoichiometry.
I did mole stuff, so anything
with mole stoichiometry.
Don't think, if I recall correct, I don't
think I did any gas law stoichiometry
or solution stoichiometry, just speaking
that it's something that usually never
is on the final when it comes to the
standardized test, and to be quite
honest, it is very, very hard, right,
and you guys are seeing that from lab
and also from class, so I think if
you can kind of understand it in those
respects when it comes to lab, I think
that's okay, I think that's good enough.
Um, for now, but just keep in mind
for anyone, for those of you, because
I'm thinking of a few of you who are
in here right now who are doing Chem
1A, we will need it for Chem 1A.
So make sure you're good with your
stoichiometry for later, because I
know at least three people in this call
are going to be in my Chem 1A class.
Um, so, or in one of the Chem 1A sections.
So make sure you're okay with, um,
doing your stoichiometry, because
it will, it gets kind of taught
really early on in that class.
Um, so we're only gonna do mass
to mass stoichiometry and the
mole to mole, I'm pretty sure.
But it doesn't hurt to kind of put
it on your flashcard anyway, just,
just in case I'm misremembering.
Being that I'd made R tests,
my other classes test, and the
resume review, so now I'm like,
which one is which in my brain?
All within the past, like,
three days, four days.
So I'm trying to make sure I
don't get them all mixed up.
And also, you know, all this stuff.
Yeah, stoichiometry is my favorite.
Uh, I don't know if that sounds sarcastic,
but usually, I don't know, a few of
you have told me stoichiometry is,
like, your actual favorite, and I'm
like, I hear that like every semester
where some people say stoichiometry
is their favorite and I'm like, man,
I must be doing a pretty okay job at
like trying to lead you guys up to it.
It's really not bad after you, once you
kind of realize that it, it really is
chemical reactions and unit conversions.
It's really all we've done before.
It's not anything new.
Um, even the mold to mold
relationship isn't new.
That's from chapter five.
It's just now we're
using chemical reaction.
Anything with mole
conversions is my friend.
Oh, no.
Well, I'm not sure anymore.
So, um, I do have a lot of recommended
problems for all those chapters.
Uh, I would make sure you're
okay with them in them.
You know that they're going to be the ones
towards the back of the test is because
it's you got to show your work for them.
Uh, biggest thing, right?
You got to write your units
for them more than anything.
Please do that.
Uh, it will Just be a disaster.
If you don't, uh, you
don't want that, please.
Oh, please.
Right.
All right.
Anything else that's on here?
I think so.
All right.
Let's go back to that module.
Um, I do have the practice exam here.
I'll add.
So these cahoots that
are here are old ones.
It's not the one we're doing tonight.
And I do post the recording and
I do edit out all like the quiet
sections, any of the timers.
You know, do the Kahoot on your own.
And then like, you know, whenever
you're stuck in a problem, I put all
the chapter markers in the video.
So on YouTube, so that way
you can fast forward right to
the question you get wrong.
So let's say if you get first
seven of them, you get right and
you're like, Oh, I'm doing great.
And then all of a sudden
you get number eight wrong.
You can fast forward right to that
specific question and see like, The
whatever, maybe whatever I do to explain
it and, you know, help you versus
watching a whole two hour recording.
Um, you know, you could watch the whole
thing if you want on like two times
speed being, I see some of you watching
so many of my videos on two times speed.
I'm like, I know I speak slow,
but I don't speak that slow.
I see how it is, but you can, you can kind
of fast forward and jump, jump around.
All right.
So the first question, all
right, we are back to that.
All right.
Back to normal.
Alright, this one, I tried to put
some theory questions on there,
being that there are a couple
multiple choices that are talking
about the basic ideas of theory
behind, um, the chemical expression.
So with this one, when it comes to a
gas, uh, if you remember, a gas does not
have a definite size, and it does not
have a definite shape, which means that
it takes the size of whatever it's in.
So, for example, if I take all the oxygen
that's around you, right, it's the size
of the room that you're currently in.
But if you take it all and you
compress it and put it in a gas
cylinder, let's say, and you want
to breathe out of a gas cylinder.
Well, you could do that, right?
So you can compress it to one location.
It's because the gas is really far apart.
And the reason you can compress
it is because it does not really
have that strong of interactions.
So they're not really, they're not
really attracted to each other.
They're not really repelling each other.
And it's because they're mainly non
polar molecules for the most part.
So that's why it is the green one.
So we like to assume that it
has no intermolecular forces.
Okay, if the atmospheric
pressure in Colorado is 0.
8800 atmospheres, what is the pressure
expressed in millimeters of mercury?
And, um, like I said, you do have
the yellow sheet for this one.
Uh, so while you're kind of going
through this review, you're welcome
to use your notes if you want to,
to help you kind of figure out where
things are and to kind of do things.
Um, but if you want to try to push
yourself, it's only use the yellow
and the in the solubility sheet.
And you maybe maybe even you have your
note card if you're really ambitious.
Then you could try doing that or maybe
write things down if you're like, Ooh,
I'm going to put that on my note card.
It's always a good idea.
It looks like pretty much
almost everybody got this one.
So which is good.
Uh, so just kind of quick little
review of how this one works.
So we're using that millimeter
mercury to ATM conversion.
Um, mostly you probably realize
that it's using that 760 millimeters
of mercury is an atmosphere.
So if you were to kind of, uh, to
go through this one, just like if
we were just to kind of see this on
our how to kind of do this one, it's
simply taking, oh, that's really big,
is taking our pressure.
So it's eight, zero, eight,
eight, zero, zero atmosphere.
And then we're just converting
it with our conversion factor.
So we set up a little tea
table and it's one atmosphere
is 760 millimeters of mercury.
Um, just kind of as a little reminder
too, that's also equivalent to
tour in case maybe you had to do a
tour conversion or, uh, Something.
So when we just times those
two together, right, so 0.
8800 times 760, you would get about 668.
8 millimeters of
Mb, your answer.
Not too bad.
Hopefully.
Okay, let's go back to our next question.
If at any point anyone has any
questions, feel free to ask me.
I know it's, it's your guy's
review as much as it's mine.
You know, I'm just trying
to come up with questions.
So ask, ask anything you want.
Sample of gas occupies 24.
5 liters at a pressure of 1.
57 atmospheres.
What is the pressure if the
volume is increased to 48.
3 liters?
Alright, so this serves for
this particular question
with question number 3.
What we're going to be looking at is
we're going to be looking at the combined
gas law in order to solve this one.
So the first thing that you always
want to do with these kind of problems
is you want to write down all the
different values that are here.
Now whether or not you realize you have to
use the combined gas law or Boyle's law,
they both would be the correct answer.
The biggest thing is, I like using
the combined gas law because it
can be used for about four or five
different, different types of problems.
Um, the biggest thing that's most
important is recognizing what is
constant, meaning what is not changing.
So in this problem, you'll kind
of see that temperature moles.
are not even mentioned in the
problem, meaning that they are what
is considered to be held constant.
They are not changing.
So our formula can evolve
into P1V1 is equal to P2V2.
So being that we are trying to solve
for the new pressure, final pressure, we
have to rearrange our equation, meaning
we have to get the pressure by itself.
So in order to do that, we need
to divide the volume by both sides
in order to cancel it out and
get the, uh, pressure by itself.
Okay.
So when we do that, we get P1
V1 divided by V2 is equal to P2.
And now what we're gonna do is
we're gonna now plug in all of
our values into this expression.
So we have 1.
57 atmospheres times 24.
5 liters, and that's
gonna be divided by 48.
3 liters.
So when we solve for that, we do 1.
57 times 24.
5 divided by 48.
3.
And what we should get for our
answer when we do that entire
expression is we will get 0.
796 atmospheres for our answer.
Now one of the things to point out
with this one is you can do some little
predictions for yourself as well.
So it's in order to
help eliminate answers.
So, if you notice that when you go from
V1 to V2, the volume is increasing.
So what happens with that?
Well, whenever volume increases,
The pressure ends up decreasing.
So if you notice, the pressure
is smaller than the number you
started with in the problem.
In the multiple choice answers,
you can eliminate about two or
three choices by just knowing that
simple fact without doing any math.
So let's say if you're short on time,
you only had a few minutes left of
your test, and you're like, Oh crap,
I got this gas law problem to do.
If you can recognize that it can
save you time, it can save you
points and get you a better grade.
Right?
So let's go to our next problem.
What volume will be occupied
by 4 grams of oxygen at STP?
Well, there's two ways to think about it.
You can either go, you can use the
ideal gas law, you could do that.
That's the longer way.
Um, it is a diatomic.
So being that that is a diatomic,
you, you gotta consider that in
terms of the molar mass, right?
So it's times 2.
So it's 15.
999 times 2.
Yeah, a lot of people
forget that one, right?
There's diatomics, it's probably
one of the biggest mistakes.
I, hell, oh my god.
How many times, how many times I made that
mistake when I was in general chemistry?
It's one of the reasons why I
tell you guys it all the time.
Because I did it too.
Everybody does it.
It's, it's the way that they exist,
that's the way we got to remember it.
Um, so when it's at SCP, the first
thing, right, your goal, when any,
with any type of stoichiometry, gas
law, is usually to get the moles.
Especially if you're going from grams
to moles, if you want to use it in
an ideal gas law or whatever formula.
So if we were to set this up right, if
I have four grams of O2, I need to con
use the molar mass to convert it, right?
So it's not gonna be 16 grams, but
it's gonna be, uh, closer to 32.
And this is for O2.
Now when we do that, the
we ha you have a choice.
You can either stop here and put it in the
ideal gas law, because STP, right, that's
the standard temperature and pressure,
so that means it's at 273 Kelvin, and
then it's also at 1 atmosphere as well.
So you can do that.
But there's an easier way, which
is when it's at STP, you can use
the molar volume as a conversion.
Then this is only for STP.
Which is when one mole of gas is 22.
4 liters.
So if you kind of remember that
one, I'll just write diatomics
in each font on my note card,
yeah, go ahead, you can do that.
So if you do 4 divided by 32 times 22.
4, you'll get roughly about 2.
80 liters as your final answer.
Um, you can plug it into the ideal
gas law too, so if you have the mole
value and plug it into PV divided by
RT, you could also, uh, or, PV divided
by RT, uh, NRT divided by P, you could
solve it that way as well, if you
wanted to, um, that's the other option.
I, I personally recommend remembering the
molar volume, it makes it a lot faster.
All right, double points
based on the following.
The gas evolved during the, during
the, oh, I guess I made a typo there.
The gas evolved from a chemical
reaction is collected at 37.
5 degrees C and 1.
024 atmospheres.
After purification, its volume
was found to be 37 liters.
How many moles of gas were collected?
And you have your R constant,
which is equal to 0.
08206.
All right, so this problem
is an ideal gas law problem.
So if you're ever given R
in a problem, it's usually,
usually it's never not the ideal gas law.
Um, it tends to be a big clue
for you, just to kind of, so
you can kind of recognize it.
The hardest part usually about the
ideal guess law, other than plugging in
everything, is probably one, making sure
you're rearranging it correctly, right?
So, dusting off the algebra skills.
Second one is making sure
all your units are correct.
So, um, the big thing
is, is that R constant?
It has the units behind it, right?
It's liters, atmosphere, mole, Kelvin.
So everything needs to match here, right?
So we have liters that matches,
atmosphere matches, Moles is
what we're trying to find.
But you'll kind of see that the Kelvin
part does not match the Celsius part.
It needs to be in Kelvin, right?
So the very first thing we want to do
is we want to convert that to Kelvin.
So if we do that, right, it's 37.
5 plus that 273.
15.
Oh, that's why she put
15 in chat, uh, 310.
65 Kelvin would be the temperature there.
And now what we're going to do is we're
going to end up plugging in all those
different pieces into the formula.
So we're going to take that, uh, we're
going to rearrange our ideal gas law.
So we're solving for n.
So when we do that, we're
dividing RT by both sides.
So it's going to end up being
PV divided by RT is equal to N.
Now it's going to be 1.
024 atmospheres multiplied by our volume.
And then all of that is going
to be divided by our, by our R
value times our, uh, temperature.
So once we plug all those values into
our calculator, what we should be getting
afterwards, let's do one times 37.
Get equal and divide by 8.
808206 times 310.
65 we should get about 1.
49 moles of our gas that is
being released in a reaction.
You think your calculator, I mean,
maybe I can always double check.
I didn't actually plug it in.
I kind of just went off what's on who,
I mean, I did it yesterday, but maybe
I could have made a mistake yesterday.
Let's double check.
I got the same thing.
So yeah, 1.
49 moles.
So it should be our answer.
If your calculator had a stroke, then,
um, probably the biggest thing, what you
might have happened is parentheses, right?
So when you're kind of plugging
these guys in, make sure you
put like the parentheses.
If you're doing it all one big operation.
You can also use the fraction
button on your calculators.
Um, if you're using a TI 36,
you have a fraction button.
I don't think I have
one on the 83 at least.
I don't know.
I've had this calculator since ever.
I don't think I've ever seen one on
here, but a lot of the calculators
do have a fraction button.
So you don't have, you can avoid that.
I ran out of time.
Yeah, I mean, I just had a timer to it.
So even mine, like if this is a test, you
know, if this was a math one, you know,
if you need a few extra minutes on it,
then And you had your, if you had all
your numbers right, and you were figuring
out them, that's the most important part.
Obviously we want to get points all
about the points about the Kahoot.
That's what it's about.
All right, well, let's go to our next one.
Okay.
Double points.
More gas laws.
Everybody's favorite.
All right.
Let's take a look at if we have a
mixture of the gases, we have oxygen,
nitrogen, and argon have a total
pressure of 800 millimeters of mercury.
If the partial pressure of nitrogen
is 80 millimeters of mercury.
And argon is 320 millimeters of mercury.
What is the partial pressure of O2?
Alright, so, way to set this
up is you're using the law of
partial pressure, so Dalton's law.
And what Dalton's law teaches us is
that if you have individual gases,
the pressure of each individual gas.
added together is your total pressure.
So for example, the total pressure that
you feel in your room isn't anxiety.
It is the pressure of oxygen, nitrogen,
CO2, and all those other gases that
are all around you, um, that are kind
of bearing down on us at all times.
Um, so with this one, it's all
about addition, subtraction.
So we have our total, which
is 800 millimeters of mercury.
Uh, we have our pressure of oxygen.
And then we have our pressure of nitrogen,
which is 80 millimeters of mercury.
And then argon is 320
millimeters of mercury.
So what we're doing is we
got to kind of rearrange it.
We got to do subtraction,
some addition, subtraction.
So being that we need to get PO2 by
itself, what we're going to end up
doing is adding the pressures on the
right, right, so that makes 400, and
then we need to subtract them from the
right hand side to get PO2 by itself.
So when I do that, we have 800 minus
400, right hand side cancels, and then
we're left with only 400 millimeters of
mercury is equal to the pressure of O2.
Okay.
So that is how you do that.
It's just a little bit of
adding, subtracting, right?
Keep in mind if you need to
cancel anything out, it's the
opposite operation, right?
With our good old algebra.
Can't go wrong there.
Uh, all right.
What is considered to be the
major portion of a solution?
We were all over the place
on this one, surprisingly.
Oh boy.
Okay, the solute is the minor component.
That's a small piece of it.
Like, for example, when we made our
solutions in lab, um, when you had those
little volumetric flasks, you added salt.
Salt was your solute.
Water, which is doing the
dissolving, is, is your solvent.
Okay, so that's the major
component is the solvent.
The solution is the
total, all of it together.
So solute, solvent, is solution.
Aqueous, all that is, for the
person to pick that, is referring
to when something is dissolved.
So it's um, whenever you have
something that is, um, going
through that dissolution, it's
being ionized, um, in the solution.
Being less stupid as we go.
Good.
And, uh, did anyone put
it was blue, blue, red.
Okay.
So people just picked Solut and solu.
I was like, good.
No one picked gas.
Well, solut is a liquid.
It's, I mean, it can be a liquid.
It's not wrong, but, oh,
it's wrong in this case.
But this, it is a term in
the for solutions, but solut
is the minor component.
Um, based on the solubility
rules, which one of these
compounds is insoluble in water?
So you got to take out your green sheet
for these, you got to figure out what's
insoluble, you better not just guess.
This is hopefully an easy question
because you have the reference.
Cahoots bring back the
elementary school vibes.
It's like, no, it's actually
the college vibes, I think.
Going backwards.
I don't know, I always kind of
feel so conflicted the fact that
I use Cahoots for my classes.
I'm like, God, I feel like my
students are going to think that
I'm, uh, I'm treating them like kids.
I'm like, I think it's fun.
I think it makes it more fun.
Okay.
It looks like everybody got this
one, which is good, but let's
still kind of talk about it.
Um, just for at least for the
recording sake, um, which so
good job figuring this one out.
Uh, big thing is, so I think,
I have, I think I have the old
version of the green sheet.
I couldn't find the current one,
so I think yours looks slightly
different, um, than the old one.
Slightly.
Um, the big thing, what you're, what
you would do with a problem like
this is you gotta look up each of the
answers, um, and you gotta break it
down into what their two ions are.
So if you go through it, the first
one is silver and bromine is what that
first one would break down into, right?
So it would be Ag plus and Br minus.
So you're looking for those
two components and you'll see
that we have a bromine, right?
So this is one of them.
And being that it's our first
choice, it's a little bit easier.
So you see that, okay, well bromine is
soluble except when it's bound to silver.
All right.
So that tells you that it's soluble.
insoluble.
So this would be a solid.
Um, the other ones like this
kind of, you know, just show
how to use it, uh, if we had to.
So the last one is sodium acetate.
So if you had to do an
acetate, that's a C2H3, O2.
So it looks like this is
what it, the molecule was.
So you see that that one's
always soluble, no matter what.
So you're just looking for like each
individual ion is kind of the idea.
Hopefully by this point,
doing those isn't too bad.
You've been through worse, especially
if you got through experiment 10,
then you're already an all star.
So good job.
Okay, which process defines how
ionic compounds break apart into
constituent ions, upon dissolution?
Let's use science terms.
We just talked about this, so what is
the actual term for what this is called?
Okay, good.
I think most of you guys got
this one, which is great.
So it maybe was a guess
if it wasn't a good guess.
I don't know.
But, uh, what's happening right
when something is being dissolved,
it's dissociating, right?
So that means it's breaking
apart into its two ions.
So it's dissociated and then afterwards
it's then ionized afterwards, but
dissociation is the first part.
Division is not a bad guess because
there's, you know, you are taking
into two pieces, um, but dissociation
is the correct term for that one.
Um, being that a You know, probably
out of all those choices, dissociation,
decomposition, or right, the two
chemical terms you've seen before.
It was one or the other, right?
So dissociation is referring to this one.
Being that they are just being
breaking apart, they're not reacting or
turning into anything new, it's just,
it's still its original components.
Decomposition would be
if a reaction happens.
Division, we'll keep
that to the math people.
They can use that term.
Multi select, double points.
Which of the following compounds
would form a hydrogen bonds in water?
So, um, how do you remember
if it hydrogen bonds?
Is that, uh, remember
F no to hydrogen bonds.
So F that.
So meaning that you're
looking for fluorine.
Haha.
Nitrogen or oxygen are the different
species you're looking for.
So, uh, whenever you're kind of looking
at these different formulas, you're
looking for nitrogen attached to hydrogen.
So you see red for an alcohol
group as OH bonded to a hydrogen.
Or you see another O
bonded to a hydrogen here.
Um, these other ones are having,
the hydrogens are attached to
the, the carbon components.
Okay.
Is that green one even real?
Yeah, no, that's real.
Um, that one is one, two,
how many carbs is that?
Uh, three, four, five,
six, seven, eight, nine.
That's nonane is the
name of that chemical.
So non, meaning nine, it's one
more carbon than octane, right?
So octane is what, uh, uh,
powers your car, right?
For gas.
Okay.
Thanks.
Good grief.
Dang it, the orange one got me.
Orange one's a good guess.
Uh, so that one, it does look like it's
bonded that way, but the way that that
structure looks like the O is like in
the middle, and then it has like two
kind of carbons kind of coming off of it.
So it's like holding hands.
Each of the carbons on both sides.
So I always like to kind of consider
that one, like where the oxygen's
like the kid and it's being like swung
by its two parents on the two sides,
. That's the way I picture those ones.
Those are known as Ether is
what that kind of chemical is.
Which one of these has
the highest boiling point?
Um, so with this guy, we, I realized I
didn't really talk about this in class,
so I did talk about it in a video though.
Um, it's a lot easier
than you might realize.
It's all about how many, how
many ions can it break down into.
So if the more ions it can break into,
break down into when it is dissolved,
then it will have a higher boiling
point or a lower freezing point.
So it's all based on how it dissolves.
It breaks down into like four ions
that's going to have a higher boiling
point than something with like.
three and something higher than
something with two and something
higher than something with one.
So we'll look at that,
we'll look at the answer.
So the first one was this one.
So if we were talking about
dissolving, it's all about how
many ions can it break down into.
So we look at our cation, right?
We have aluminum three plus and
we would have three nitrate ions.
So the way I like to think about these.
Is if you take the molecule
and then you shatter it, right?
Like it's a piece of glass, how
many pieces can it break into?
So when you're looking at the math here,
you're just adding the coefficients.
So we have 1 plus 3, that means we have 4.
So we're just comparing
that number with each one.
So like if I look at the next
one, right, Na2SO4, well how many
pieces do I have for this one?
Well I have 2 sodiums and then 1 sulfate.
So what would that, what
would that end up being?
This would be 2 plus 1.
is equal to.
So, so far, this one,
so far, is the highest.
Now, when you're comparing other
ones, well, oh my god, oh yeah, we
need the bunny as the morale boost.
Oh my god, that bunny is so freaking cute.
Um, comparing to other solutions, uh,
the lowest one is always going to be
pure water because it doesn't dissociate
into anything other than water.
Um, after that, the other ones that
don't dissolve, so they, well, they
dissolve, but they don't break down.
So, like sugar, for example, sugar
will dissolve, but it doesn't ionize.
So it just turns into an aqueous solution.
So this is what we call a non electrolyte.
So this one would be just equal to one.
So you're comparing like
that number for each one.
So whatever is the highest number.
So the first one that we did was four.
That one would be the most
ions out of all of them.
So that's what you're just comparing.
It's not terrible, but it's not,
um, unless you know the trick.
Um, so what this thing is called,
these numbers here, these are
called ionization factors.
So if you've ever seen that word on
a homework before, um, it's called
an ionization factor, meaning like
how, how much of it's ionized.
The bigger that ionization factor, usually
the, like the better it is at conducting
electricity in terms of solution.
So that's kind of the whole idea.
I think Alize just needs to post more
pictures of her bunny in the discord
pets channel because the only one that
has really done anything is Jackie in
that channel with her cat and that was
adorable but I think more bunnies and more
animals on that channel would be great.
Calcium bromide is used in lithography.
Um, and photography.
So what is the morality of a
solution prepared by dissolving
45.38 grams of cadmium bromide in
375 grams of water morality, right?
It smalls a solu over
kilograms of solvent.
So the solvent, so Ute in
this case is cadmium bromide.
So the first thing that we need
to do is we need to look up the
molar mass of cadmium bromide.
Um, does anyone in, out, then any of
you actually happen to calculate it?
Because I did not.
We could do it though.
272.
21 sounds reasonable.
Did you end up getting the
answer correct over there?
Then you probably did.
If you do, you didn't get it right.
Uh oh.
All right, we'll see.
277.
2 grams of cadmium bromide.
So when we solve for this
part, right, we're going to
calculate how many moles we have.
So we do 45.
38 divided by 272.
22.
And what we should get is 0.
1667 moles of our solute.
And we're going to be dividing
that by our solvent kilograms.
So being that our solvent is 375.
We need to convert that to kilograms.
So we'll just divide that by a thousand.
So that will be 0.375 kilograms.
So when we divide 0.1 6, 6 7 divided
by 0.375 should get 0.4446 figs.
So we got four, six figs,
4, 4, 5, uh, modality.
Usually we use a cursive M to do that one.
So, which I.
Mine, I guess, I guess we must have
rounded something a little off.
So we 6 as our answer.
So, all right, so we have molality.
So, uh, our next one, let's
see, are we still on solutions
or are we past solutions?
Double points.
More solutions.
I think we have one or two more solutions.
Potassium fluoride is
used for frosting glass.
Calculate the molarity of a
solution prepared by dissolving 39.
3 grams of potassium fluoride.
and enough water to produce
325 milliliters of solution.
With this, right, we need our formula.
Um, we have molarity,
which is moles over liters.
So the first thing we were given
is we have our mass of RKF.
So what we have to do is we
have to convert that to moles.
So I, I already looked up the, uh,
or looked up, I calculated the, uh,
Molar mass of potassium fluoride,
right, so using our periodic table.
So we'll convert this to moles.
So it's gonna be 58.
098 grams KF, and then we'll
just convert that real quick.
So that'll be 39.
3 divided by 58.
098.
So what we should get for that is 0.
6764 moles.
of kF.
And if you have more digits, even better.
And then what we're going to do with
that number is we're going to divide
it by our liters of our solution.
So we had 325 milliliters.
Um, so we would divide that by 0.
325 liters.
When we do that, we should
get a molarity of 2.
08 moles over liters, which is 2.
08.
Big M.
Alright, what volume of a 3.
25 molar solution of HCl is
required to make 300 milliliter
dilution with a concentration of 1.
34 molar solution of HCl?
So how would we make a dilution?
Alright, um, with this one, right,
we have the following problem.
So it says, the big thing is
we're going to be using dilution
formula, but the, there's two
things that are the hardest part.
is one, you need to make
sure two of your units are
cancelling, so they have to match.
So like in this case, the
molarities are matching, right?
So they'll cancel.
If you have the volumes, they
need to be the same unit.
Um, so when you're reading these problems
carefully, It doesn't really matter
if you get the ones and twos mixed.
What it does matter is if you get, you got
to make sure you get the pairs correct.
So in this case, it says what volume of 3.
25 molar.
So that means that these
two are paired together.
Doesn't matter if you label it
as one or two, That volume, that
concentration, they're together.
So you don't know what
volume of C one or of that C.
You have that concentration.
Then it says, and you want to make
300 milliliters is what your goal is.
So you have a volla of 300
milliliters and you wanna make
this specific concentration.
So what we're gonna do is we
gotta rearrange our formula, plug
it in, we're solving for V one.
So it's going to be a C2 V2 is all
divided by C1 to get V1 by itself.
So what we'll end up doing, um, is we're
going to end up kind of plug it all in.
Right.
Um, Yeah, C1V1 or M1V1, they're
the same, they're the same formula.
Yeah, so this is the same thing.
You do M1V1 is M2V2.
Um, the exact same formula.
So when you plug it in, it's 1.
34 molar times 300 mLs, all
divided by, 3.25 molar and it
should be a smaller volume.
'cause you're talking about
the original solution.
So you're taking from your
stock bottle in this case.
So when we do the math, we get roughly
about 123.6, or sorry, 123.7 milliliters.
We'll round that up to
three dec or three six figs.
We have 124.
Hopefully that matches my key.
Okay, good.
It does not have to be
converted to liters.
No, you do not have to as long as if
you're given a problem like this, if,
let's say if they're both milliliters,
they have to both be either both
be milliliters or both be liters.
Um, it doesn't as long as they cancel.
It's kind of like, um, the
gas laws are the same way.
The combined gas law, they
don't have to be in liters.
If you do the combined gas law,
they As long as your units cancel,
but if it's something where you're
like, I just want to convert it every
time for myself, some consistent,
I don't see a problem with that.
If you want to put in leaders every
time, I mean, if it makes you do
it correctly every single time,
do it until you're comfortable.
In a balanced chemical equation,
which statement best represents
a balanced chemical equation?
Uh, this one is kind of, it's really
wordy, um, but really the whole
idea is when you're looking at a
chemical reaction, it has the same
number of atoms of each type of
atom on the left and the right side.
So like if you have 10 carbons
on the left, you have 10 carbons
on the right, 6 oxygens on the
left, 6 oxygens on the right.
It's the number of atoms
that you're looking for.
Um, consider the balance
equation shown and identify
the statement that is not true.
This one was a little quick,
so I apologize for that one.
I should give you guys like
an extra minute with these.
Um, so let's just kind of
go through it together.
So the first one said the
coefficient of sodium sulfate is one.
So with this one, what makes it
hard is if you're still not the most
literate when it comes to chemical
naming, um, that realistically chemical
naming does come down, comes to time.
The longer you kind of speak the language,
the fat, the better you'll get at it.
It's true for any language, right?
For a few, um, like for if any
of you, I know a couple of you in
class are learning, um, You know,
Spanish or American sign language,
or maybe you learned English, you
know, maybe it's your, maybe English
is your second or third language
and, you know, it just takes time.
Uh, same with chemistry, right?
You'll get it down whether you get
it here or physio, it'll just take
a take, you know, a few classes and
it'll, it'll come second nature.
So sodium sulfate is this one, right?
It's one on the left.
So you can see it's a coefficient of one.
So that's true.
barium sulfate is produced in solid form.
So barium sulfate is our product.
We see it's solid, so that's true.
Then it says 2 NaCl
also could be written as
Na2Cl2.
We never, ever, ever, ever do that.
We don't carry out the two, like in
terms of counting atoms, sure, you could
say there's two sodiums, two chlorines,
but you don't actually physically carry
out that operation mathematically.
Um, the two represents you have two moles
or two molecules of sodium chlorine.
I'm sorry, chloride, um, in the molecule.
Um, so that one's your answer, but this
is a kind of go through the other ones.
It says barium chloride
is dissolved in water.
So BACL2, right?
It's aqueous.
So that's tell you.
Yep, that's true.
And it says the products.
Okay, so with this one, because I'm
kind of, I don't know how many of you
guys are maybe not the best with that.
terminology, right?
When we talk about the reaction yield
arrow, the right side is the products.
The left side is the reactants
and what we're starting with.
So the products are sodium
chloride and barium sulfate, which
so that statement is also true.
I like balancing makes sense to me.
It's a risk a little bit of the
team assessment is all balancing
So if you're really good at
balancing, then you're good to go.
Have a good night I'll say thank you
so much for being here and you can
always finish it on the recording and
stuff like that So have a good night.
Thank you for sharing your bunny
showing us Keep sending pictures.
It makes my day whenever I see the bunny
All right, let's do our Next one.
I really like the one the purpose
of that one is So the peach is the
name of okay, damn should be molecule
So the neck so that one kind of helps
you a stoichiometry because that's
the whole idea Stoichiometry is like
trying to read a chemical equation.
What does it mean?
Um when the reaction shown is correctly
balanced Coefficients or what?
Sorry, there should be a deeper.
So how would you balance
the following or not?
So all these numbers are your coefficient.
So balance it like normal, uh,
and then look at the answers.
And I should have given
you more than 60 seconds.
I apologize for that.
So, okay, let's see.
So this one, okay, looks like everybody
that was able to answer got it correct.
Um, if you're still working on it,
um, you know, no need to worry.
That's, you know, like I said, I
kind of, you'd have, you can use,
you got more time on the test, right?
If you kind of think about it, you get
about, you know, two or three, about two,
three minutes per question on the test.
So you get a little bit more time.
And some of them are theory questions.
So hopefully like you would
know them right off the bat.
So you get more time on others.
Um, the trick on this one, Uh,
as realistically as thinking
about evening the odds.
So if you kind of remember my list of
tricks I kind of tell, I had in my videos
for Saturday and then had um, in um, in
class when we talked about balancing, one
of the most common ones you'll hear me say
a lot is, oh, you got to even the odds.
So in, in usually that's
referring to oxygen.
Oxygen is notorious for having
an odd number next to it.
So you see, we have.
Three oxygens here.
So what that means is we need
to make it even, especially when
we have an even number on the
right side in the form of O2.
So the first thing we can do is if
we add a two in front of that, um,
what we're going to see is that, all
right, well, if I have six oxygens
as a result of that, I'll put a three
in front of O2 and then I'll put, uh,
then I'll put a two in front of KCL
and then it's gonna be all balanced.
So it's gonna be a 2, 2, 3.
Going to be my coefficients.
So sometimes starting on the oxygens
and evening the odds can be like
the, can be the easiest way to
kind of see it really quickly.
Especially when you see like
the KCL is already balanced.
You're like, oh, we're good to go.
Um, but the oxygens tend
to be kind of a problem.
Um, this was one of the reactions you did.
This was station, um, 5 for lab 10.
I believe that's station 5.
One of you guys burned
with the Bunsen burners.
When the reaction shown is correctly
balanced, the coefficients are what?
Balance it.
There is one trick that I
kind of mentioned to you guys.
Uh, I don't know if I mentioned
it in the videos for Saturday.
I, I don't remember if I did or not.
Um, I do remember saying it for Monday,
Wednesday, because I made sure I said it.
Um, with this one, when it's all
Pluses and minuses for the charges.
Does anyone remember if you need
coefficients, if it's all plus ones
and minus ones, it's already going
to be balanced as your final product.
So whenever it's all plus ones,
minus ones, it's already balanced.
So meaning you don't have
to do anything for it.
It's, it's, uh, it's a, it's
an amazing trick to know.
Um, cause it could save you a lot of
time of trying to checking everything.
So it's whenever all the charges are plus
one, minus one, it's already balanced.
Um, and this is the case for, um, it's
probably not the case all the time.
I'm sure there's, I'm sure there,
there's going to be one of you is going
to find something where it doesn't, but
it's, it works for double displacement.
For sure.
Okay.
So whenever you have that AB
plus CD, um, it always works.
Um, so you'll see over
here, it's still plus minus.
And then if you, and you're
like, wait, what about H2O?
Well, if you write it as HOH,
right, as for the balancing,
it's still plus and minus.
So it never changes charge.
The only time that it can become an
issue is if it's oxidation reduction,
and then you got to make sure, but
that's not with double displacement.
That is with um, a single and
decomposition and combustion.
The following reaction can be
classified as what type or types
of reaction can you say this is.
The first one I was hoping you'd
notice is a double displacement.
So if you were able to kind of
get to that, then, you know,
you, you got, uh, almost the way.
So a double displacement would be like
the acid base one, um, in this case.
So, uh, with it, right, we see it has
a 3 plus, uh, minus, uh, plus, 2 minus.
So it's following A, B, C, D.
So now with that, how, what can
we go after that particular fact?
Well, with this, you see
that it has a H plus.
And then OH minus in the reaction.
So we have a base and then
an acid being added together.
And so, and you can see that
it's making a salt and water.
So that is our acid base reaction.
Um, now precipitation is
whenever we are making a solid.
So one of the, uh, products, I believe
the, um, at least I'm hoping, I'm not just
guessing, but this says solid next to it.
Yes, it does.
So aluminum sulfate says solid next to it.
So that tells you, hey, you
have a, you have a chunk of
something in your test tube.
This is a solid that is forming.
So when you write out the, uh, net ionic
equation for it, it would reflect that
solid and the liquid forming in this case.
Okay.
So it's both.
So it's both acid base and precipitation
because you happen to make both.
Yeah, know your classifications that way
because there are, I asked a couple of
them, at least two or three questions
that are like, can you tell me what
kind of, the typical oxidation reduction
reaction, the electrons are transferred.
I know Leo goes, well, that's the answer.
You know, it's kind of how this is
trying to explain, Leo goes grr.
So, uh, with this one, just
kind of think about it.
Uh, so here we'll go to tablet,
and you guys should be able to
see the question on your end too.
Um, so we're trying to
think of Leo goes grr.
So how can we try to understand,
uh, how can we phrase that?
So when we have, attempt to draw, try my
best, when we have a chemical, so let's
say if we have A plus B, Well, one of them
is going to be transferring a electron.
So if we're thinking about how is,
we're too high with wording, Dr.
Dan, I, I have lots of expectations.
I believe in you guys.
You guys are great.
When we're talking about how
things are transferred, the one on
the, on the left hand side, this
one is, A is transferring to B.
So is A losing an electron,
or is it gaining an electron?
Let's start with that.
What do you guys think?
Is it going through oxidation,
or, or is it losing or gaining?
Let's just do that.
It's losing.
Right, exactly.
So being that this is losing one, that
means that this one is going through
oxidation, and then this guy over here
is gaining one, so this is being reduced.
So on the problem, it says, uh, the
correct answer is, so it's saying
the electrons are transferred.
So that means it's being transferred
from what is being oxidized.
So on the left hand side, this is
oxidized and it's being transferred
to what is being reduced.
Okay.
So that, that's what,
where that, that goes from.
It kind of does mean the opposite
of what you had to think, right?
So it's, It's, it's
losing, but it's giving it.
It's doing it voluntarily.
It's not that it wants to, but, so
it's going from one to the other.
Uh, when it comes to knowing this, I
don't, you know, the thing is I need to
talk to the physio teachers how much.
You need to know oxidation reduction
because when you guys do the electron
transport chain, and you will, and you
learn about the co-enzyme of the body.
So when you learn about NAD and
FAD, which are your B vitamins,
which the system metabolism, it's
all oxidation reduction reaction.
Um, so, uh, when you could, when
you go through, through all that,
um, I have a feeling you've probably
gotta know at least the basics of it.
At least when you kind of see it.
Why would gaining be called reduction?
I don't know.
Maybe it's like reduction of number
because it's going becoming more negative.
I never actually thought about it before.
What's negative is good
when it comes to electrons.
It's true.
So I don't know.
Maybe because it's reducing
the number because it's going
like to the more negative side.
So maybe that's considered a reduction.
Oxid, oxidation, the reason why it's
oxidizes, usually ox, anything with oxygen
is typically what's losing the electrons.
Usually it's where that one comes from.
I don't know.
I never, I never thought about it before.
You gave me a question I
never thought about before.
I'll have to look into it,
see if I can figure it out.
Oxidation is positive, so the
electrons are leaving the party.
Oh my god.
In which of the following is the
oxidation number of oxygen equal to zero?
For oxidation numbers, when
something was equal to zero was when
it's found in its natural state.
This is the way that I like to phrase
it, meaning it's found as, like,
it's metallic form, so if it's like
a solid metal, or if it's found in
its diatomic form, is the other one.
So, um, in terms of, um, diatomic
oxygen, nitrogen, or any of those
gases, The molecule as a whole
has an oxidation number of zero.
Um, being that it is a covalent
bond, so we would have it as
that oxidation number is zero.
Um, in terms of H2O2, it
actually, the oxygen does have a
covalent bond, a covalent number.
It's still a It's actually negative one
in that, in that example for oxygen.
The net ionic reaction for
the balanced chemical equation
shown below is, uh, what?
So, this one you have three minutes, so
see if you can figure out the balance.
Or the net ionic equation.
So this one actually does have
a trick to it, uh, but we'll
go through the long way too.
So the trick is, if you kind of
notice, I already gave you the phases
on it, um, which means if you already
have the phases you don't have
to go through the entire process.
of um, figuring out what's
soluble and insoluble.
So you can actually kind of cut
to what the final answer is.
And this is very common on the
standardized test and also on um, even
on sometimes my exams too, because I saw
that the standardized tests, the final
does this, is it gave you all the phases.
So what that means is when we get
to our final answer, the net ionic
equation It has to show you creating
something, meaning it's always gonna
show you making a solid, a liquid or gas.
Um, unless it's no reaction.
So it's gonna show you
that or no reaction.
It has to be one of those four things.
So being that we have a solid, which
is a G two SF four, this thing is going
to have to show you making that thing.
So how would you make that?
Well, that means you would
need two silver ions.
and a sulfate ion, which
is your yellow answer.
Um, but if you were to do this right
from, from top to bottom, how would
you go through and show all the steps?
Um, if you didn't know that you'd
have to look up the solubility, right?
So you'd look up each one of
these chemicals, you'd determine
if it's soluble or not.
Um, and then you would
break down all the ions.
So we'd have like two silvers, two
nitrates, We'd have two potassiums,
sulfate, um, then we'd have the other
side, which is two potassiums, two
nitrates, and then our, um, Ag2SO4, right?
You never break apart
solids, liquids, or gases.
But then what we're going to do is we're
going to look for everything that matches.
So we'll see like the nitrates match,
then we got the potassiums match.
So then the only things left
are that reaction that I drew
at the very bottom, right?
Everything else Is, uh, still,
still, uh, still what remains.
So the things I highlighted
are our spectator ions, right?
So if you were asked a question
like, What are the spectator ions?
Well, that's going to be anything
that you that you highlight.
It's just what's watching, it's not
what's actually doing the reaction.
Um, or if you're asked like, what
is created, then like, what's
the precipitate, for example,
then this would be your answer.
So like, if we were to evaluate this
question, or if it asks you like, what gas
is evolved, then you could maybe ask that
if it was a different type of reaction.
So there's all kinds of things that
you could, that could be asked, you
know, and that kind of type of thing.
If that makes sense.
Spectator irons are on the bench, right?
Yeah, they're not actually doing anything,
they're just on the bench the whole time.
The combustion of propane gas
is used to fuel barbecue grill.
In order to produce 5.
65 moles of water, how many
moles of oxygen gas are needed?
There's, so when you do
stoichiometry, there's really four
major conversions that you're going
to be doing more than anything.
That's molar mass, right, which is
when we talk usually about a solid,
typically a solid, not always,
but it's referring to a mass.
mole to mole, right?
So when you're using the chemical
equation, right, to describe
going from one mole to another.
Molarity, which is moles to liters.
And then the last one,
which is aqueous, right?
So anything that's liquid.
And then PV is equal to nRT, which
is a gas, um, that's moles to liters.
Now this one, so to kind of
bring up the, uh, the prompt,
it said we wanted to make 5.
65 moles of water.
And we want to know how many
moles of oxygen there are.
Well, all we have to do is
a mole to mole conversion.
So if we have mole of water, we
want to convert to moles of O2.
So what are we going to use to do that?
Well, we're just going to read
our chemical equation, right?
So if I have four, if I have
four moles of O2, water that
is equivalent to 5 moles of O2.
So our moles will cancel of water.
So all you do is 5.
65 times 5 and then divide it by 4.
Not that bad.
So when we do that we should get 7.
06 moles is our answer.
Don't overthink a problem.
Wow.
It was like, it's not that bad, I promise.
Um, so make sure you're okay with
doing the mold to mold conversion one.
You don't want to get this one wrong,
because they're, if they're, they're,
I'll give you, you know, you guys
are hearing probably, I don't know
how many people watch the whole
recording, but if, uh, this one,
you will have to do a mold to mold
conversion, just a basic one like this.
You don't want to be, you
don't want to overthink it.
You want to get those easy
points, easier points, right?
compared to the other stoichiometry ones.
What mass of oxygen gas is required to
react with calcium metal to produce 44.
8 grams of calcium oxide?
Let's talk about it.
So, with this problem, Uh, this one is
very much a, uh, Chem 1A problem, uh,
being that it has, meaning Chem 1A is
for the majorist level chemistry, um, it
has a lot of unknowns about it, right?
You have to do a lot of things.
Um, the first thing you gotta do
is you gotta be able to figure out
what the chemical equation, which
alone can take some, a lot of time,
you know, to interpret and read it.
Um, then you gotta figure out the molar
masses and then do the stoichiometry.
So it's like a three step problem.
Um, and that's, you know, that's not even
including how many math steps there are.
So usually I give you a little bit
more information if this wasn't a test.
Um, this kind of problem could be
on there, but I would give you more
pieces, like whether I give you the
molar mass, or I would maybe give
you the chemical equation, or, or
something to kind of speed you up on it.
Um, so with this one, the first one is,
um, predicting the chemical equation.
So it said you had calcium reacting with
oxygen gas, so, and it made calcium oxide.
So calcium oxide is C A and O next to each
other, and then we have to balance it.
Okay?
So to balance it, you need a 2 to
balance, remember, even the odds.
So we want to even out the oxygens.
And then we'll need a 2 in front
of calcium, so we have that.
Now the next part is whenever we
need to figure out how many grams
of oxygen we have, I figured out the
molar masses for us, um, already.
So we're always going to start with the
term that's by itself, which is our 44.
8 grams of calcium oxide.
What we're going to do is we're going
to set up a stoichiometry expression.
Using our t table.
So the first thing we need
to do is cancel out grams.
So in order to do that, we need to use the
molar mass of calcium oxide, and that's
equivalent to one mole of calcium oxide.
All right, so when we do that,
we see that our units cancel.
Now in order to do the mole to mole
portion, this is where we use our
chemical, our chemical equation.
Right, so two moles of calcium oxide
are equivalent to one mole of oxygen.
So what we'll do is we'll write
down that we have two moles, CaO,
that's equivalent to one mole O2.
Then once we cancel out that portion,
we then need to find our mass
part, which would be the last part.
So then that's where we use the
other molar mass, that's here.
Um, so if I kind of move this over a
little bit, make that a little tinier,
we'll plug in our last molar mass.
So one mole is equal to 31.
998 grams of O2.
Now that we have all of our pieces,
right, those will cancel too.
Um, what we would do is we
multiply everything on the top.
So it'd be 44.
8 times 31.
998 grams.
And we would divide that by 56.
079 times 2, and what we will get is 0.
399 grams of O2 is needed
for this reaction to happen.
And that's kind of how, so this
one is probably like, this is
your standard, what we call the
mass to mass stoichiometry, right?
So this is kind of the one thing that
you want to make sure you do know how
to do is the mass to mass portion of it.
Like I said, I would probably only have
you do like pieces of this, whether
if, if this was a question, maybe it
might be like writing the reaction out.
Or doing the stoichiometry, I wouldn't,
I don't throw them all in one problem.
So don't kind of worry about like,
oh, I didn't even know where to start
and how to predict it, like the other
things, it would be one piece of it.
Um, uh, at a time in the, you know, most
of you guys, as I kind of tell many other
faculty, you know, you guys are brand new
to most, you're brand new to chemistry.
You never, maybe most, you
never took chemistry before.
So let's, let's treat it like that, right?
You're learning the basics.
So one thing at a time, and then
we combine it together into one A.
We had the following equation represents
the formation of nitrogen dioxide.
It's a major commo component of smog.
If 0.68 moles of no is reacted
with 0.79 moles of O2 to produce
NO two limiting reactant is what?
So this one we have a
limiting reactant problem.
It's similar to the one
that we did earlier.
Not the last problem,
but the one before that.
So what we need to do is we need to find
the number of moles of NO two, but we need
to do it with each starting reactant and
figure out which one will run out first.
So if we do, let's say, NO
first, so 0.68 moles of nno, we
want to convert that to NO two.
So 2 moles of NO equivalent
to 2 moles of NO2.
And we'll see like, hey, this
cancels, uh, this part cancel.
The 2s cancel, so it's going to
be the same kind of number, right?
So it's going to be 0.
68 moles of NO2.
The other one, right, we have 0.
79 moles of O2, and we'll do
the same conversion, right?
So it's, in this case, it's one mole of
O2 is equivalent to two moles of NO2.
So we'll have one mole, we'll
have one mole on the bottom,
that's going to two moles of NO2 on top.
So we do 0.
79 times two, so it's going
to be a bigger number, right?
So that's going to be 1.
58 moles.
So which one is our limiting reactant?
Well, it's always the one
that's smaller, right?
So the 0.
68 moles is the, it's going to be the
smaller amount that we can possibly make.
So that means that our limiting
reactant is, is NO, which would
have been the blue answer, right?
So that's kind of, that's the whole idea
here is whatever one is the smaller one.
And this kind of problem you
can do to mass as well, right?
You can figure out, um, which
one makes a smaller mass.
You can do it with volumes.
There's all kinds of ways
that you can make this problem
harder, um, if you wanted to.
So, limiting reactant problem,
there will be one on the test.
There has, there has to be one.
Like, you can't go through a
chemical test without doing one.
As I kind of say, the titration is
a rite of passage, um, a limiting
reactant problem is, is on there too.
A reaction produces ammonia.
The theoretical yield is 420 grams.
What is the percent yield if
the actual yield is 350 grams?
It's always the actual divided
by the theoretical times 100%.
So the actual is what you
are doing in lab, right?
So that's what you find.
The theoretical is your, um,
is your stoichiometry number.
So if you're ever asked to find the
theoretical yield, that means do
stoichiometry is what that tells you.
Okay.
So with this one, uh, the
actual yield was three 50.
We would divide that by four 20, three
50 divided by four 20 times a hundred.
And what we would end up getting is 83.
3 percent would be our answer.
And that would be a very, very good
deal to actually get for an experiment.
Consider the reaction shown.
You have N2 plus O2 makes 2NO.
You have a delta H, 43.
2 kilocalories.
When 50 grams of nitrogen reacts,
how many kilocals will be created
and how will, is it released?
Is it absorbed?
How would you word how this is showing?
So that has to do with if
it's exo or endothermic.
Okay so with number 27, our last problem,
how exactly do we go through solving this?
So there's a couple things to point out.
The first one is our
enthalpy value, our delta H.
In this case if you notice that it's
positive, So what that means is that
the heat in this case is endothermic.
Or whenever something is endothermic, that
means it's being absorbed in the reaction.
So in our reaction, heat is
gonna be a reactant in it.
So that helps you eliminate
essentially three out of five
of the choices by knowing that
alone reaches really, really nice.
So when we're doing this, we always
start with the term that's by
itself, which is our grams, right?
So what we're gonna do is our
goal is to convert this to moles.
So we'll take our 50 grams of N2,
and we're going to convert that
to moles using our molar mass that
was given to us in the problem.
So we have one mole of N2, and the
way that we can end up using this term
over here, this enthalpy term, is it is
equivalent to the number of moles of each
item in the chemical equation, right?
So it's equivalent to the coefficient.
So in this problem, there is one mole
of nitrogen based on that coefficient.
So one mole is equivalent to
positive 43.1 or 0.2 kilo cals.
So what we'll do is we'll take 50,
we'll multiply that by the 43.2.
And then we're going
to divide it by the 28.
1, 014.
So when we do that, we're
going to get a positive 77.
1 kilocals as our answer.
So it was absorbed, and we had 77.
Okay, thank you so much for listening
and let's go to our conclusion.
So I hope that this did end up helping
so you understand kind of the basics
here of really all the little pieces
and bits of, of the different process.
Um, so good job everybody
for participating.
Um, if you need help at all studying,
uh, you guys are welcome to, uh,
send me emails, you can message me
on discord, you can, um, follow if
you want, you can comment in the
YouTube video description if you want.
I end up ranting on there too to people.
Uh, there's all kinds of ways that
you can try to try to get in touch
with me, whatever makes it easier.
If you want to, you can go through
this again on your own, um, way
after you kind of study a little bit.
So this is, um, in order, the one
I, what I used to make this one is
an old test So this will kind of,
um, it kind of gives you an idea.
This is probably, I'd say it's similar
to the difficulty of ours, but there's a
couple of questions like that I pointed
out that I think are a little bit harder.
Then, um, then what you, what
you're going to get on this one.
So like other ones, I pointed out the
stoichiometry once, but I hope that
helped and thank you guys for listening.
I appreciate it as always.
Well, thank you all so much for listening.
If you made it to the end of this video,
then you thank you all for watching.
I hope that this helped.
Um, if you have any questions, please
comment below in the, in the section
below, if this is your first time
here and you're part of my class
or another class, Please hit that
like, hit that subscribe button.
I appreciate all your support.
You guys are wonderful as
always, and I hope to see you
all again later in the future.
I'll see you all later.
Bye now.